Harsha Varma, Josh Hilliard, and Justice Adams
CS 4550 Compilers
Grammar Revision Explanation
Fall 2017



For the non-terminal NONEMPTYFORMALS, a tail of NONEMPTYFORMALS-TAIL was added to remove the ambiguity of two paths for a FORMAL call potentially needing to be called.  This was done by Left Factoring

     <NONEMPTYFORMALS> ::= <FORMAL> <NONEMPTYFORMALS-TAIL>
<NONEMPTYFORMALS-TAIL> ::= , <NONEMPTYFORMALS>
                         | ε


For the non-terminal EXPR, a tail of EXPR-TAIL was added.  This expression had left recursion with EXPR being called for 2 of the 3 cases.  SIMPLE-EXPR was used for the initial state needed because unless the program is infinitely long, it will need to call a SIMPLE-EXPR at some point.
                <EXPR> ::= <SIMPLE-EXPR> <EXPR-TAIL>
           <EXPR-TAIL> ::= < <SIMPLE-EXPR>
                         | = <SIMPLE-EXPR>
                         | ε


For the non-terminal SIMPLE-EXPR, a tail of SIMPLE-EXPR-TAIL was added.  This expression had left recursion with SIMPLE-EXPR being called for 3 of the 4 cases.  TERM was used for the initial state needed because unless the program is infinitely long, it will need to call a TERM at some point.

         <SIMPLE-EXPR> ::= <TERM> <SIMPLE-EXPR-TAIL>
    <SIMPLE-EXPR-TAIL> ::= or <TERM>
                         | + <TERM>
                         | - <TERM>
                         | ε


For the non-terminal TERM, a tail of TERM-TAIL was added.  This expression had left recursion with TERM being called for 3 of the 4 cases.  FACTOR was used for the initial state needed because unless the program is infinitely long, it will need to call a FACTOR at some point.

                <TERM> ::= <FACTOR> <TERM-TAIL>
           <TERM-TAIL> ::= and <FACTOR>
                         | * <FACTOR>
                         | / <FACTOR>
                         | ε


For the non-terminal FACTOR, a tail was added for the IDENTIFIER terminal, as both an IDENTIFIER with nothing after it as well as an IDENTIFER ( ACTUALS ) could be used.  Since this is ambiguous, IDENTIFER was consolidated into one state, and a tail named FACTOR-ID-TAIL was added.

              <FACTOR> ::= if <EXPR> then <EXPR> else <EXPR>
                         | not <FACTOR>
                         | <IDENTIFIER> <FACTOR-ID-TAIL>
                         | <LITERAL>
                         | - <FACTOR>
                         | ( <EXPR> )
      <FACTOR-ID-TAIL> ::= ( <ACTUALS> )
                         | ε


For the non-terminal NONEMPTYACTUALS, a tail of NONEMPTYACTUALS-TAIL was added to remove the ambiguity of two paths from the EXPR call.  This was done by Left Factoring

     <NONEMPTYACTUALS> ::= <EXPR> <NONEMPTYACTUALS-TAIL>
<NONEMPTYACTUALS-TAIL> ::= , <NONEMPTYACTUALS>
                         | ε

